<poem>
    ENGLISH EXCERPTS
    
    BOOK 1 LINES 192-210
    <excerpt>
        <body>
            <line>Then back to <noun>shore</noun> <pronoun>he</pronoun> <verb>sped</verb>, and to his <noun>friends</noun></line>
            <line><verb>distributed</verb> the <noun>spoil</noun>, with that rare <noun>wine</noun></line>
            <line>which good <name>Acestes</name> while in <noun>Sicily</noun></line>
            <line>had <verb>stored</verb> in <noun>jars</noun>, and prince-like <verb>sent away</verb></line>
            <line>with his Ioved <noun>guest</noun>;—this too <noun>Aeneas</noun> <verb>gave</verb>;</line>
            <line>and with these <noun>words</noun> their mournful <noun>mood</noun> <verb>consoled</verb>.</line>
            <line>“<noun>Companions</noun> mine, <pronoun>we</pronoun> <verb>have</verb> not <verb>failed</verb> to <verb>feel</verb></line>
            <line>calamity till now. O, ye have borne</line>
            <line>far heavier sorrow: Jove will make an end</line>
            <line>also of this. Ye sailed a course hard by</line>
            <line>infuriate Scylla's howling cliffs and caves.</line>
            <line>Ye knew the Cyclops' crags. Lift up your hearts!</line>
            <line>No more complaint and fear! It well may be</line>
            <line>some happier hour will find this memory fair.</line>
            <line>Through chance and change and hazard without end,</line>
            <line>our goal is Latium; where our destinies</line>
            <line>beckon to blest abodes, and have ordained</line>
            <line>that Troy shall rise new-born! Have patience all!</line>
            <line>And bide expectantly that golden day.”</line>
            <line>Such was his word, but vexed with grief and care,</line>
            <line>feigned hopes upon his forehead firm he wore,</line>
            <line>and locked within his heart a hero's pain.</line>
        </body>
    </excerpt>
    
    BOOK 2 LINES 200-233
    But now a vaster spectacle of fear
    burst over us, to vex our startled souls.
    Laocoon, that day by cast of lot
    priest unto Neptune, was in act to slay
    a huge bull at the god's appointed fane.
    Lo! o'er the tranquil deep from Tenedos
    appeared a pair (I shudder as I tell)
    of vastly coiling serpents, side by side,
    stretching along the waves, and to the shore
    taking swift course; their necks were lifted high,
    their gory dragon-crests o'ertopped the waves;
    all else, half seen, trailed low along the sea;
    while with loud cleavage of the foaming brine
    their monstrous backs wound forward fold on fold.
    Soon they made land; the furious bright eyes
    glowed with ensanguined fire; their quivering tongues
    lapped hungrily the hissing, gruesome jaws.
    All terror-pale we fled. Unswerving then
    the monsters to Laocoon made way.
    First round the tender limbs of his two sons
    each dragon coiled, and on the shrinking flesh
    fixed fast and fed. Then seized they on the sire,
    who flew to aid, a javelin in his hand,
    embracing close in bondage serpentine
    twice round the waist; and twice in scaly grasp
    around his neck, and o'er him grimly peered
    with lifted head and crest; he, all the while,
    his holy fillet fouled with venomous blood,
    tore at his fetters with a desperate hand,
    and lifted up such agonizing voice,
    as when a bull, death-wounded, seeks to flee
    the sacrificial altar, and thrusts back
    from his doomed head the ill-aimed, glancing blade.
    then swiftly writhed the dragon-pair away
    unto the templed height, and in the shrine
    of cruel Pallas sure asylum found
    beneath the goddess' feet and orbed shield.
    Such trembling horror as we ne'er had known
    seized now on every heart. “ Of his vast guilt
    Laocoon,” they say, “receives reward;
    for he with most abominable spear
    did strike and violate that blessed wood.
    Yon statue to the temple! Ask the grace
    of glorious Pallas!” So the people cried
    in general acclaim.
    
    BOOK 4 LINES 679-713
    Her sister heard. Half in a swoon, she ran
    with trembling steps, where thickest was the throng,
    beating her breast, while with a desperate hand
    she tore at her own face, and called aloud
    upon the dying Queen.
    “Was it for this
    my own true sister used me with such guile?
    O, was this horrid deed the dire intent
    of altars, Iofty couch, and funeral fires?
    What shall I tell for chiefest of my woes?
    Lost that I am! Why, though in death, cast off
    thy sister from thy heart? Why not invite
    one mortal stroke for both, a single sword,
    one agony together? But these hands
    built up thy pyre; and my voice implored
    the blessing of our gods, who granted me
    that thou shouldst perish thus—and I not know!
    In thy self-slaughter, sister, thou hast slain
    myself, thy people, the grave counsellors
    of Sidon, and yon city thou didst build
    to be thy throne!—Go, fetch me water, there!
    That I may bathe those gashes! If there be
    one hovering breath that stays, let my fond lips
    discover and receive!” So saying, she sprang up
    from stair to stair, and, clasping to her breast
    her sister's dying form, moaned grievously,
    and staunched the dark blood with her garment's fold.
    Vainly would Dido lift her sinking eyes,
    but backward fell, while at her heart the wound
    opened afresh; three times with straining arm
    she rose; three times dropped helpless, her dimmed eyes
    turned skyward, seeking the sweet light of day, —
    which when she saw, she groaned.
    Great Juno then
    looked down in mercy on that lingering pain
    and labor to depart: from realms divine
    she sent the goddess of the rainbow wing,
    Iris, to set the struggling spirit free
    and loose its fleshly coil. For since the end
    came not by destiny, nor was the doom
    of guilty deed, but of a hapless wight
    to sudden madness stung, ere ripe to die,
    therefore the Queen of Hades had not shorn
    the fair tress from her forehead, nor assigned
    that soul to Stygian dark. So Iris came
    on dewy, saffron pinions down from heaven,
    a thousand colors on her radiant way,
    from the opposing sun. She stayed her flight
    above that pallid brow: “I come with power
    to make this gift to Death. I set thee free
    from thy frail body's bound.” With her right hand
    she cut the tress: then through its every limb
    the sinking form grew cold; the vital breath
    fled forth, departing on the viewless air.
</poem>